Walter Craig Barber papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Walter Craig Barber Papers
1918-1945
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Barber, Walter Craig
0.50 linear foot (1 box)
Biographical Sketch
Walter Craig Barber was born about 1920 in Waterbury, Connecticut. His father, Walter Barber, was a surgeon. The younger Walter went by his middle name of Craig. During World War II, Craig served with the 5th Armored Division, Company C, 127th Ordnance Maintenance Battalion.
Scope and Content
The museum and library jointly purchased this collection. Uniforms, a duffle bag, and patches went to the museum. Photographs were transferred to the Graphics Department and the printed and manuscript material went to the library.
Barber’s papers consist of a diary, 1944, only portions of which were used, mostly for listing locations in which the army found itself and for his ruminations. The bulk of the incoming correspondence is a series of newsletters, The Merriman Chronicles, written by a friend from Waterbury describing life at home and his sons' experiences in the war. A letter dated June 12, 1945 celebrates the end of the war in Europe while one dated September 2, 1945 expresses relief at peace with Japan.
Outgoing correspondence includes a letter to Barber's sister, Betsy, dated 1945; a polemic concerning extended service in the army, 1945; an undated postcard of a bridge in France; and a letter to Mme. Kroonen et Rose, in French, also undated.
Military documents include an identity document permitting Barber to carry and dispatch mail, 1942, a customs declaration, and a pass for three days in Paris. Two spiritual texts were given to Barber from his church and are inscribed to him. His portable desk or writing portfolio still contains stationery. Printed materials include a map of the "Advance of the 5th Armored Division, Seine River to the Rhine," a service manual, a history of the 5th Armored Division, bulletins, and three issues of Victory News, the newspaper of the 5th Armored Division.
World War I memorabilia include a soldier's songbook, 1918, and a photographic postcard showing Dr. W. Craig Barber operating on a patient in Lyon, France.
A Brooklyn Dodger's program from a game against Philadelphia in 1946, and eight issues of Stars and Stripes were transferred to other institutions, namely the Yogi Berra museum and Hofstra University
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Barber, Walter
Geographic Names
Connecticut -- History -- World War, 1914-1918.; Connecticut -- History -- World War, 1939-1945
Contents:
- Papers
  - Diary, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1945 outdated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Military documents, 1942 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gifts, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Writing portfolio (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed U.S. Army information (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Victory News," August 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorabilia from World War I, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)